A Guide to the Merton Elbridge Church Family, 1858-1995
Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Merton Elbridge Church Family, 1858-1995
Falls Church History Room, Mary Riley Styles Public Library
Record Group 6-6
3 boxes; 2 linear feet
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records at the Falls Church History Room were donated by Melvin Steadman. The two scrapbooks of (Merton) Elbridge Church were donated by Henry Douglas.
M. E. Church's records were donated to the University of Virginia Library in 1988 by Beverley T. Steadman. This is the link to the guide to the papers at UVA: https://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaxtf/view?docId=uva-sc/viu02223.xml
Biographical Note
Merton Elbridge Church (M.E. Church) trained as a pharmacist and ran a drugstore in Falls Church for 12 years. He helped start the first telephone company in the area which was later absorbed by the Chesapeake & Potomac Telephone Company. He also organized the Arlington and Fairfax Railway Company. He entered the real estate and insurance business and helped develop the Sherwood Subdivision. These are just a few of the many accomplishments and community services he was involved in throughout his life.
Merton Elbridge Church was born in Derby Line, Vermont, on February 14, 1858. He moved to Virginia in 1879 and settled in Falls Church in 1886. He married Carrie Bell Northrup in 1884, and they had two children, Guy Northrup Church and Maybelle Amelia Church. M.E. Church died on September 16, 1931 in Falls Church; Carrie Church died on May 31, 1935.
Guy N. Church, Sr., was born July 26, 1889 and died April 7, 1964. He is buried in Arlington National Cemetery. He married Mary Emilie Torryson on September 28, 1909. They had two children: Merton Elbridge Church (known as Elbridge and Guy Northrup Church, Jr. (went by Northrup).
Maybelle Amelia Church, born on January 26, 1900, married Kenneth Norman Mills in 1923. There are no files for her, but she is mentioned in correspondence with both her father and brother.
[Merton] Elbridge Church II was born January 5, 1912 in Falls Church, and died August 26, 1992. He is also buried in Arlington National Cemetery. He served in the Army for twenty years and retired as a Lieutenant Colonel.
Guy Northrup Church, Jr., was born April 3, 1914 in Falls Church. He was married to Mary Ann Redington on March 29, 1939. Guy died on December 30, 1995, in Evans, Georgia; Mary Ann died on March 26, 2004.
Scope and Content
Most of the records involve the real estate business of Merton Elbridge (M.E.) Church, the bulk of which include copies of deeds in which M.E. Church was the trustee, buyer and/or seller. There are also files on his interests in local railways and the Falls Church Telephone and Telegraph Company. Also includes files for son and grandsons.
Most of the records involve the real estate business of M.E. Church, the bulk of which include copies of deeds in which M.E. Church was the trustee, buyer and/or seller. There are also files on his interests in local railways and the Falls Church Telephone and Telegraph Company.
Of special interest are the abstracts of title in the deed series, especially File 10 in Series 2 which shows the disposition of the property that became the Sherwood subdivision. There are also some copies of deeds concerning the Sherwood Subdivision in File 6-6-1-27.
Arrangement
The files were divided into five series, two for Merton Elbridge Church, one for his son (Guy Northrup Church, Sr.) and two for his grandsons. Series one is organized alphabetically. The deeds in M.E. Church's files were placed in a separate series (Series 2) and organized by date. Many of them involve the Sherwood Subdivision of houses in Falls Church. This new arrangement was thought to be more useful to the researcher.
The files on Guy Church, Sr., are arranged alphabetically. Pages from a scrapbook make up the bulk of the Merton Elbridge Church (grandson) files; there is only one file for Guy Church, Jr.
Contents List
- Box 1
  - Series 1: Merton Elbridge Church, 1858-1935
    - Biographical information, 1889-1931 (Folder 1)
    - Estate (Folder 2)
    - Atwell [Gertrude] vs Crossman [Anne F.], Legal Documents, 1895-1896 (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1922-1930 (Folder 4)
    - County Recording Fees, 1920, 1922, 1927 (Folder 5)
    - Falls Church Telephone and Telegraph Company, 1901, 1916-1917 (Folder 6)
    - Grandison, Caroline, Insurance Policies and receipts, 1913-1919 (Folder 7)
    - "Group of Business Buildings for M.E. Church" (publication), [n.d.] (Folder 8)
    - Henrietta Clewes Estate, Settlement, [1908] (Folder 9)
    - Invoices, 1910 (Folder 10)
    - Invoices, 1920-1922 (Folder 11)
    - License Applications, 1894-1895 (Folder 12)
    - Membership cards and drivers' licenses, 1903, 1920, 1928 (Folder 13)
    - Myers, Charlotte E., Property Sale, 1893-1894 (Folder 14)
    - Pharmaceutical business, 1920-1922 (Folder 15)
    - Photograph, M.E. Church, Inc., Realtor, [1924?] (Folder 16)
    - Railroads – Arlington and Fairfax Railway, 1928-1929 (Folder 17)
    - Railroads – Fairfax, Potomac and Washington Electric Railway, 1902-1903 (Folder 18)
    - Railroads – Falls Church and Potomac Railroad Company, 1896-1903 (Folder 19)
    - Railroads – Right of Way, 1877-1900 (includes complaint of trespass against Church & others) (Folder 20)
    - Railroads – Washington and Marlboro Electric Railway Company, 1895 (Folder 21)
    - Railroads – Washington, Arlington and Fairfax Railway, 1896-1903 (Folder 22)
    - Railroads – Washington, Fairfax and Alexandria Railway Company, 1892 (Folder 23)
    - Railroads – Washington-Virginia Railway Company, 1882, 1920-1929 (Folder 24)
    - Real Estate – Inquiries, 1908-1918 (Folder 25)
    - Real Estate – Trustee Sale, 1922 (Folder 26)
    - Sherwood Subdivision, 1891-1922 (Folder 27)
    - Sherwood Subdivision, Lot owners, Transfer fee and taxes, 1893 (Folder 28)
    - Tax Receipts, 1885-1894 (Folder 29)
    - Tax Receipts, 1895-1900 (Folder 30)
    - Tax Receipts, 1901-1910 (Folder 31)
    - Tax Receipts, 1911-1916 (Folder 32)
    - Tax Receipts, 1917-1919 (Folder 33)
    - Tax Receipts, 1920-1921 (Folder 34)
    - Taxes, 1903-1928 (Folder 35)
    - Tripp Correspondence (see also Library of Virginia papers), 1917-1918 (Folder 36)
- Box 2
  - Series 2: Merton Elbridge Church, Deeds, 1858-1935
    - Deed, R. G. Walrad and Margaret A. Walrad to Spencer A. Coe, March 10, 1875 (Folder 1)
    - Deed of Release, George B. Ives, Trustee, J. C. DePutron, Administrator of Rexford Hatch (deceased), and Spencer A. Coe, March 15, 1875 (Folder 2)
    - Indenture, Cassius Carter, Special Commissioner, to John S. Garrison, September 26, 1881 (Folder 3)
    - Deed, Spencer A. Coe and J.H. Gray, Trustee, to William H. Torreyson, October 6, 1882 and Deed of Release, April 30, 1886 (Folder 4)
    - Deed, Spencer A. Coe and Katharine W. Coe to Seth Osborn, May 4, 1886 (Folder 5)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), John S. Garrison and Annie T. Garrison and E.J. Northrup, Trustee, for Seth Osborn, October 22, 1887 (Folder 6)
    - Deed, John S. Garrison and Annie T. Garrison to S.V. Proudfit, April 9, 1889 (Folder 7)
    - Deed, Seth Osborn and Mary E. Osborn, to Sarah E. Bell; and Deed of Trust (Indenture), Sarah E. Bell and William S. Bell; N.F. Graham and Geo. B. Ives, Trustees, for Seth Osborn, October 18, 1889 (Folder 8)
    - Deeds and Articles of Agreement, Charles Bendhiem [sic], Jacob C. DePutron, Mary E. DePutron, Schuyler Duryee, A. A. Freeman, and Merton E. Church, June 24, 1890 (Folder 9)
    - Abstract of Title, Sherwood tract, (120 acres), 1828-1890, held by J.C. DePutron, Trustee, April 25, 1891 (Folder 10)
    - Article of Agreement between Myron Brinkerhoof and E.E. Reed, and J.C. DePutron, Schuyler Duryee, A.A. Freeman and M.E. Church, May 16, 1891 (Folder 11)
    - Statement of Title, 1847-1891, for Harry D. Gordon and Fulton R. Gordon, May 26, 1891, and September 22, 1891 (Folder 12)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture) and Promissory note, Henry D. Gordon, Isabel J. Gordon, and Fulton R. Gordon; William McPyncheon and George A.L. Merrifield, Trustees, for Clara Isabella Merrifield, May 29, 1891; Bond and Deed of Release, Henry D. Gordon, Isabel J. Gordon, Fulton R. Gordon, and Le Geneva Gordon to Clara Isabella Merrifield, October 16, 1891 and December 15, 1894 (Folder 13)
    - Deed of Sale, Jacob C. DePutron, Trustee for Mary E. DePutron and Merton E. Church, to Sarah Lloyd, June 15, 1891 (Folder 14)
    - Deed (Indenture), A.A. Freeman and Martha E. Freeman, to Merton E. Church, June 24, 1891 (Folder 15)
    - Indenture (Joint Deed), Jacob C. DePutron, Trustee for Mary E. DePutron and Merton E. Church, and Jos. S. Riley and Mary E. Riley, July 20, 1891 (Folder 16)
    - Deed, Schuyler Duryee and Margaret A. Duryee to Jacob C. DePutron, October 8, 1891 (Folder 17)
    - Receipts, Geo. B. Ives and M.E. Church, October 31, 1891 and November 30, 1891 (Folder 18)
    - Survey for M.E. Church, for land adjoining the Sherwood Subdivision, November 13, 1891 (Folder 19)
    - Deed, Jacob C. DePutron, Trustee, and Schuyler Duryee and Margaret A. Duryee, to Mary E. DePutron, March 3, 1892 (Folder 20)
    - Deed, John Hammond and Addie L. Hammond, and Jacob C. DePutron, Trustee for Mary E. DePutron and Merton E. Church, April 1, 1892, and Cancelled Deed, John Hammond, Jacob C. DePutron, Mary E. DePutron and Merton E. Church, April 1, 1892 (Folder 21)
    - Abstract of Title, 1840-1892, and drawing, John Hammond to J.C. DePutron, April 12, 1892 (Folder 22)
    - Deed of Exchange, Jacob C. DePutron, Trustee, and Joseph S. Riley and Mary E. Riley, September 16, 1892 (Folder 23)
    - Abstract of Title. 1850-1889, Edmond C. Bittenger Estate, April 1, 1893 (Folder 24)
    - Articles of Agreement, Merton E. Church acting for Mary E. DePutron and Jacob C. DePutron and Daniel O. Monson, Agent for A. A. Freeman, February 24, 1894; and Articles of Agreement, Daniel O. Monson Acting for A.A. Freeman and Martha E. Freeman, and Mary E. DePutron, Jacob C. DePutron and Merton E. Church, February 24, 1894 (Folder 25)
    - Report of Survey, A.A. Freeman's portion of the Sherwood Subdivision, March 8, 1894; and Deed of Partition, A.A. Freeman and Martha E. Freeman by Daniel O. Monson, and Mary E. DePutron, Jacob C. DePutron and Merton E. Church, March 20, 1894 (Folder 26)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), Walter H. Magruder and Minnie Magruder to T. M. Talbott and J. C. DePutron, Trustees, October 6, 1894, and letter to Walter H. Magruder from M. E. Church, November 12, 1919 (Folder 27)
    - Deed of Exchange, Jacob C. DePutron and Mary E. DePutron, Merton E. Church and Carrie B. Church, Schuyler Duryee and Margaret A. Duryee, A.A. Freeman and Martha E. Freeman, and Daniel O. Monson, Attorney; Deed of Exchange, Jacob C. DePutron, Trustee, Mary E. DePutron, Merton E. Church, and Carrie B. Church; and Articles of Agreement, Merton E. Church, Mary E. DePutron and Jacob C. DePutron, December 12, 1894 (Folder 28)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), William S. Bell and Sarah E. Bell, N.F. Graham, Trustee, for George B. Ives, October 12, 1895 (Folder 29)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), Merton E. Church and Carrie B. Church, George W. Mankin, Trustee, for William H. Nowlan; Receipt, April 1, 1896; Deed of Release, George W. Rankin, Trustee and William H. Nowlan, Beneficiary, to Merton E. Church, May 25, 1903 (Folder 30)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), Annie E. Webb and J.W. Webb and Merton E. Church, Trustee, for M.J. Laughlin and H.M. Newcomb, May 1, 1897 (Folder 31)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Jacob C. DePutron and Mary E. DePutron to Merton E. Church, November 21, 1898 (Folder 32)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), S.V. Proudfit, Merton E. Church, Trustee, to Charlotte E.D. Swigett, February 13, 1899; Deed of Release, December 15, 1899 (Folder 33)
    - Receipt, M.E. Church on deed from J.C. DePutron, March 23, 1899 (Folder 34)
    - Deed Fee Simple, S.V. Proudfit and Amy W. Proudfit to Mary G. Sims and Merton E. Church, November 1, 1899 (Folder 35)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), S.V. Proudfit and Amy W. Proudfit, Merton E. Church, Trustee, to Lyman Ballard, December 15, 1899; Receipt, December 15, 1899 (Folder 36)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Bird M. Robinson and Randolph Barton, Receivers, and Baltimore Building and Loan Association to Merton E. Church, November 2, 1900 (Folder 37)
    - Deed of Trust, Sarah E. Bell and W.S. Bell and William M. Ellison, Trustee, for Mary E. Osborn and Julia Osborn, October 18, 1904; Receipt, October 18, 1904 (Folder 38)
    - Deed, William S. Bell to Sarah E. Bell, October 28, 1905 (Folder 39)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Mary E. DePutron, Merton E. Church and Carrie B. Church to George L. Erwin, November 14, 1905; includes Survey of Erwin Lot in the Sherwood Subdivision by Henry Crocker, Surveyor, October 7, 1905; Receipt, October 18, 1905 (Folder 40)
    - Deed, Merton E. Church and Carrie B. Church to Joseph C. Murray, March 31, 1906 (Folder 41)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Annie E. Webb and J.W. Webb, and William M. Shafer, Trustee, for Fred E. Parker, April 16, 1906; Deed of Release, May 1, 1907 (Folder 42)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Mary E. DePutron, Merton E. Church and Carrie B. Church, to R.C. Lowe, October 24, 1906; Quit Claim Deed, Jacob C. DePutron, Trustee, Mary E. DePutron and Merton E. Church, October 24, 1906 (Folder 43)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Fred E. Parker and Marcia C. Parker to Elizabeth S. Fox, May 1, 1907 (Folder 44)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Sarah E. Bell and Eli J. Northrup, August 31, 1907 (Folder 45)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), Fred E. Parker and Marcia C. Parker and C.E. Gay, Trustee, for Bertha M. Parker, December 2, 1907; later for Amanda B. Fisk, May 1, 1909; Deed of Release, C.E. Gay, Trustee, to Fred E. Parker and Marcia C. Parker, October 14, 1918 (Folder 46)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Fred E. Parker to Marcia C. Parker, February 20, 1908 (Folder 47)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Eli J. Northrup to Rose I. Thompson, and Deed of Release from N.F. Graham, Trustee, November 1, 1910; Survey for E.J. Northrup, November 2, 1910 (Folder 48)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Mary E. DePutron, Merton E. Church and Carrie B. Church, to Townson O. Marr, November 25, 1910 (Folder 49)
    - Drawing, Lots outlined by the Falls Church and Georgetown Road, Mount Olivet Rd, Sommers Tract and Greenough's Rd, June 14, 1913 (Folder 50)
    - Article of Agreement (Sale Contract), Merton E. Church to Georgiana Taylor, January 2, 1914 (Folder 51)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), Solomon H. Lomax and Merton E. Church, Trustee, for A.M. Hess, May 1, 1915 (Folder 52)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Merton E. Church and Carrie B. Church to Solomon H. Lomax, May 1, 1915; Notice of Cancellation, May 31, 1918 (Folder 53)
    - Article of Agreement, M.E. Church and George Thomas, June 1, 1918 (Folder 54)
    - Abstract of Title, 1851-1918, Prepared for Merton E. Church for land conveyed to Fred E. Parker from Annie E. Webb, October 23, 1918; Continuation of Abstract of Title, Fred E. Parker and Marcia C. Parker to Gordon Maury Kingman and Frances Wingate Kingman, February 26, 1921 (Folder 55)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), Gordon Maury Kingman and Frances Wingate Kingman; Merton E. Church, Trustee, for Marcia C. Parker, October 25, 1918 (Folder 56)
    - Article of Agreement (Sale Contract), Carrie B. Church and Merton E. Church to Gilmer Nickell, May 1, 1919 (Folder 57)
    - Deed of Trust and Installment Note, Marion Smith and Elmira J. Smith; Dr. James B. Gould, Trustee, and Falls Church Bank, Inc., August 25, 1919 (Folder 58)
    - Deed, Charles H. Buxton and Helen L. Buxton to Ernest E. Oswald, November 4, 1919; Deed, Ernest E. Oswald and Gladys B. Oswald and F.S. McCandlish, Trustee, for Atlantic Life Insurance Company, July 15, 1920; Contract for house construction, Ernest E. Oswald and Mack Smarr, August 24, 1920; Title, 1869-1919; Release Deed, A.D. Christian and F.S. McCandlish, Trustees, Ernest E. Oswald and Gladys B. Oswald, and Atlantic Life Insurance Company, July 22, 1922 (Folder 59)
    - Deed of Release, William M. Ellison and Joseph L. Shockey, Trustees to H.A. Shockey, February 19, 1920 (Folder 60)
    - Deed, Merton E. Church and Carrie B. Church to Marion Smith, October 9, 1920 (Folder 61)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), Gilmer Nickell and Mary V. Nickell; Merton E. Church, Trustee, for Carrie B. Church, January 1, 1921 (Folder 62)
    - Letter, J.C. DePutron to Merton E. Church, January 24, 1921 (Folder 63)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), R.C. Staebner and Estelle E. Staebner; Merton E. Church, Trustee, for Etta F. Emerson, March 1, 1921; Receipts, March 21, 1921 and May 26, 1922 (Folder 64)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), R.A. Cushman to Merton E. Church, Trustee, for J.C.M. Valentine, April 2, 1921; Deed Fee Simple, J.C.M. Valentine and Isabel M. Valentine to R.A. Cushman, April 2, 1921 (Folder 65)
    - Deed and Letter, Merton E. Church and Carrie B. Church to Jacob C. DePutron, July 28, 1921 (Folder 66)
    - Deed, Mary E. DePutron, Merton E. Church, and Carrie B. Church to Mary E. DePutron, October 1, 1921 (Folder 67)
    - Deed of Trust, Gilmer Nickell and Mary V. Nickel to Merton E. Church, Trustee, for Falls Church Bank, May 2, 1922 (Folder 68)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Estelle E. Staebner and Ralph C. Staebner to William F. Moses and Moffett W. Moses, May 18, 1922 (Folder 69)
    - Abstract of Title, 1865-1922, Prepared for land conveyed to Robert A. Cushman and Emma K. MCL. Cushman from Thomas M. Jones, July 25, 1922 (Folder 70)
    - Deed Fee Simple, Gilmer Nickell and Virginia Nickell to Carrie B. Church, November 8, 1923 (Folder 71)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), Martin I. Cook and Elizabeth H. Cook to Merton E. Church, Trustee, for Wilmer H. Case, August 1, 1924 (Folder 72)
- Box 3
  - (Continued) Series 2: Merton Elbridge Church, Deeds, 1858-1935
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), William F. Moses and Moffett W. Moses to Merton E. Church, Trustee, for W. S. Hoge, Jr., January 29, 1925 (Folder 73)
    - Deed of Trust, Lee D. Hall and Bertha C. Hall to Charles W. Steer and Charles S. Muir, Trustees, for Birdella R. Roberts; Deed of Trust Note, Charles S. Muir and Charles W. Steers to Birdella R. Roberts, January 22, 1926; Statement dated October 4, 1927 (Folder 74)
    - Certificate of Title, 1924, Issued to Birdilla R. Roberts for property owned by Lee D. Hall, October 3, 1927 (Folder 75)
    - Deed Fee Simple, James E. Scott and Dolores M. Scott to Nettie E. Bowden, June 15, 1928; Deed of Trust (Indenture), Nettie E. Bowden to Merton E. Church, Trustee, for James E. Scott, June 15, 1928 (Folder 76)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), Ann Bryan and Ethel Reid to Merton E. Church, Trustee, for James E. Scott, July 3, 1928 (Folder 77)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), Evan T. Davis and Louise D. Davis to Merton E. Church, Trustee, for Lester D. Seymour, August 15, 1928 (Folder 78)
    - Deed of Release, William F. Columbus, Trustee, for Harry E. Besley, Beneficiary, to Lee D. Hall, August 21, 1928 (Folder 79)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), Katherine B. Curry to Merton E. Church, Trustee, for W.S. Hoge III, November 1, 1928 (Folder 80)
    - Deed of Trust (Indenture), Evan T. Davis and Louise D. Davis to Merton E. Church, Trustee, for Lester D. Seymour, July 1, 1930 (Folder 81)
    - Notes of deeds on card advertising Union Revival Services at Crossman Methodist Episcopal Church, June 12, 1922; Notes of deed on membership card for the Lincoln-Lee Legion, September 18, 1925 (Folder 82)
- Box 3
  - Series 3: Guy Northrup Church, Sr., 1889-1964
    - Bank Statements of Condition, Invoices, Correspondence, 1920-1928, 1937 (Folder 1)
    - Civil Defense, 1950 (Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Maybelle C. Mills (sister), 1946-1956 (Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and other papers, 1941-1947 (Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and other papers, 1950-1959 (Folder 5)
    - Correspondence and other papers, 1960-1961 (Folder 6)
    - Deeds, 1933-1935 (Folder 7)
    - Deposition, Brush Tract, [n.d.] (Folder 8)
    - Invoices, 1950-1959 (Folder 9)
    - Newspaper clippings, Obituary, 1957-1964 (Folder 10)
    - Photographs of houses and people, several of Church, others unidentified and undated (Folder 11)
- Box 3
  - Series 4: Merton Elbridge Church, 1912-1992
    - Scouting certificates and awards, spelling awards, membership cards, 1928-1939 (Folder 1)
    - Scrapbook, Part One, 1925-1937 (Folder 2)
    - Scrapbook, Part Two, 1937-1939 (Folder 3)
- Box 3
  - Series 5: Guy Northrup Church, Jr., 1914-1995
    - Deed of Gift, (copy, not signed) 1990 (Folder 1)
    - Paperweight with photograph of Merton E. Church advertising the Falls Church Telephone & Telegraph Co. (Folder 2)